♪ In the not-too-distant
future ♪
♪ next sunday, a.d. ♪
♪ There was a guy named joel ♪
♪ not too different
from you or me ♪
♪ he worked
at gizmonic institute ♪
♪ just another face
in a red jumpsuit ♪
♪ he did a good job
cleaning up the place ♪
♪ but his bosses
didn't like him
so they shot him into space ♪
♪ we'll send him
cheesy movies ♪
- ♪ the worst we can find ♪
- ♪ la la la ♪
♪ he'll have to sit
and watch them all ♪
- ♪ and we'll monitor his mind ♪
- ♪ la la la ♪
♪ now, keep in mind
joel can't control ♪
- ♪ where the movies
begin or end ♪
- ♪ la la la ♪
♪ because he used
those special parts ♪
♪ to make his robot friends ♪
Let's go.
- Cambot.
- Pan left.
Hi, girl.
What a cool guy.
A wisecracker.
♪ If you're wondering how
he eats and breathes ♪
- ♪ and other science facts ♪
- ♪ la la la ♪
♪ then repeat to yourself,
"it's just a show ♪
♪ "I should really
just relax ♪
♪ for mystery
science theater ♪
♪ 3000 ♪
All right, f-stop at 5.6.
For maximum depth of field.
Okay, that looks good.
Okay, 5.6
at, let's see here, eight feet.
That comes
to roughly a.S.A. Of 200.
Okay, adjust lighting
to full lumens
and a cone focus.
That looks good.
Okay, bring around
the back drops.
Stay cheery, everybody.
Okay.
Oh, hi, everybody.
Welcome to the satellite
of love.
I'm joel robinson,
and I just thought
it would be nice
to get a nice picture
of the boys
to have around the house,
so I'm taking their portrait,
and I'll be with you
in a minute.
Could we just go, please?
- Order. Order.
- Stop it, you two.
They were like this
all the way over.
- You guys, listen--
- cut it out, fembot.
We are going to get
a nice picture
of this family
if it kills us.
- [Blows raspberries]
- Crow.
- Hey, what?
- Crow, where are those nice
pants I bought you?
- I don't know.
You can't walk around
wearing a sport coat
without your nice pants.
Can we just go?
Commercial sign in 10 seconds.
Say cheese.
Okay. Now, come on, you guys.
Shape up, face cambot.
Come on, gypsy.
Get in here.
Oh, my hair.
Hold it.
Hey. The light meter, joel.
- Oh.
- [Shutter clicks]
[All groan]
Joel. Joel.
Ooh, snicker snacks.
Joel.
Chocolate milk...
You guys, would you please get
back into position?
Come on, knock it off.
- Joel, I just--
- gypsy, come on.
- Speed and chim-chim
are calling.
- Stop it.
Okay, thanks a lot.
Sorry about the tip.
I left the money in my other,
uh, pocket.
Oh! Hi, joel.
How you doing?
We'll be with you
in one second.
Clayton. Here, boy.
Come here, clayton.
Here, boy.
Here, clayton.
Give me one good reason
why I shouldn't kill you,
frank.
Well, the stuff is here.
The stuff that we ordered--
just in time
for the invention exchange.
You go first, pumpkin pants.
Well, your ample ones.
My invention exchange
this week
dynamically blends martial arts
with snacking.
It's called snaction,
and it makes snacking fun.
Here's a snaction favorite--
the wax knuckles.
All right?
And here's one.
It's called a pixie staff.
[Grunts]
It's a pixie stick
filled with delicious
straight sugar.
See? Okay?
And, hey, crow.
Hey, crow.
What are these here?
What are these?
- What are which ones?
- What are these?
Oh, them are the five lady
fingers of death.
Five lady fingers of death.
You get it?
And this is based
on a chuck norris movie.
It's called the everlasting
octa--gobstopper.
You get it?
Oh, and these are ninja
throwing cookies.
Hey, those are delicious.
You see, everybody
doesn't like some things,
but nobody
doesn't like bruce lee.
Ouch.
Uh-oh, I broke him.
Oh, well, that's really great,
joel,
but we've got something
going down here
- that's really special.
- Tell them, frank.
Well, dr. Forrester
has taken the money
from my 401 k
and sunk it into these
fast-food novelty items,
which he's just sold
to a major, major buyer
who shall remain nameless.
Well, actually
that fell through,
but I'm sure
they're going to sell.
You see, joel,
they're called unhappy meals.
You took my money and you
haven't sold them yet?
Oh, quit whining, frank.
As an example, joel.
This one comes
from the restaurant
with a cold
hamburger sandwich
with a bite taken out of it,
some floor sweeping compound,
a couple of dead silverfish,
and a rusty suture needle.
You took all my money,
you son of a...
Watch it, frank.
Now, there are many
different styles, joel.
For instance,
this one comes with a maze,
and you try to get
the motorcade
past the book depository.
[Chuckles]
And then this one comes
with a used q-tip.
Ooh, that is unhappy.
Isn't it?
And then there's one
with a roach motel,
and, well, you get the idea.
What do you think?
I think it's evil
and it'll never sell.
Yeah, and give frank
his money back.
Yeah.
Oh, blow it out your--
experiment today
is a swedish fantasy called
the day the earth froze,
but first a short,
apply titled
"here comes the circus,"
and I hope it goes down hard.
- Push the button, frank.
- No, I want my money back.
Forceps, frank.
Pain.
I don't care.
I want my money.
- Electroshock for a--
push the button.
- No! No!
The box, frank.
Push the button.
Yes...
[Mutters]
- [Alarm blaring]
- [All yelling]
Ow. Owy.
Think you broke my bone.
Here comes the devil!
[Cackles]
Beelzebub the clown.
Guys, can we be just a little
less dark with this short?
Dark?
Dark.
There's excitement everywhere.
The circus is here.
Everyone is headed
for the big top
to thrill to and cheer
the funmakers, daredevils,
freaks and ferocious
performing animals.
And here come the freaks now.
Look at them all.
It's a dime for some candy
and maybe a tummy ache
tomorrow.
Chug it! Chug it chug it!
Cannonball! Cannonball!
[Belches]
Peanuts for the elephants.
Now, folks,
step right this way
to the bigger, better,
more exciting side show.
Now, here's the deal.
Just four years.
Christmas present coming.
...time to see it all.
Get your red hot moms.
...lovely little lady
on my right.
She performs
her own tracheotomy.
Ooh.
[Chuckles]
And she's cute, too.
Ew. Ugh.
The snake charmer
extraordinary.
- Now for the big show.
- The hell?
The event that the kids
and the grownups
have been waiting
for for months.
No one's going to tell
a navy man when he's had
enough to drink.
- [Belches]
- ...Proudly presents
the magnificent and gorgeous
inaugural pageant.
Look, it's thomas edison
with his electric child.
Supporters drummed up for
the spanish-american war.
Hey, wait a minute.
Aren't the horses supposed
to go behind the band?
Whoops.
Now make way
for the ku klux clowns.
Whoo!
Yes, children of all ages
are confronted by forces
they can't begin
to understand.
Cigars? Hi, everybody.
Okay, guys, you're too dark.
Would you lighten up?
Hey, look.
It's rue mcclanahan.
It's ezekiel,
that amish clown.
No buttons.
Look, it's ice princess zebra.
Hey, it's emmett kelly.
- That's good.
- No, it really is.
Whatever, joel.
Aah! Jeez.
Aah!
It's liza!
- Aah!
- No!
...headed by the world famous
clown emmett kelly.
See? Emmett changed management
soon after this.
Oh, we love it when he eats.
Introducing miss betty rich,
queen of the air
in a sensational display
of breathtaking aerial feats
without a net below.
For the first time in america,
miss betty rich.
Would someone give me
a hand here?
Ooh, betty got back.
I'll say.
It's a living!
Mother, please come home.
Yes, our betty swings
both ways.
Oh, stop it.
She does.
Look.
Listen, you hit the floor
a couple of times,
you make sure
you get it right.
Yeah, see?
This takes care of unwanted
hair in the bikini area.
Oh! Oh! Oh! Oh!
Oh! Oh! Oh! Oh! Oh!
They take a licking
and keep on ticking.
Women who love too much
and the feat that use them.
This one's on the rebound.
And now the only girl to a
complete summersault
too high to the feet
of the balancer.
This act was outlawed
on several continents.
Here is the man who mistook
his wife for a hat.
- Hi, rick.
- Sarah.
Flipped her off.
Sorry, wayne.
This is for the ladies only.
The celebrated
rieffenach troupe,
bareback riding marvels
whose equals do not exist.
Grace and beauty
of equestrianism.
On your head
if you're squeamish.
Yes, this act embodies
the sadness that is circus.
- That is true, dog.
- Hey, sorry.
What? What?
Is all he does is eat?
- He's good at it.
- What?
The beautiful bareback riding
ballerina miss lucy.
Could not be with us
tonight,
so we have this act.
You're next up there.
And now, ladies and gentlemen,
- we present the...
- [Laughing]
Whoa, oh.
Whoo!
Uh. Whoa.
- Whoa. Whoa.
- I thought that was
another ball!
Here come the comics of the
air,
the dexterous and hilarious
feat high above the... bar.
Store this image away
for a later nightmare.
- I invented that move.
- Yeah, right.
Levis loose-fitting
clown jeans.
Huh?
Oh, no, no, no.
They're doing it clown style.
No!
And madonna thinks
she's innovative.
Oh, please tell me
this isn't happening?
Oh, no.
More, more.
I'm a bad clown.
Yes, children's windows
of perception
are open for only a second,
only to take in the horror
that is the circus.
High above the crowd,
dag hammarskjold
takes to the trapeze.
Yes, it's albert speer nude
donning a dance belt.
In the center ring,
the only group of pamalino
liberty horses in the world.
Tamed and presented
by adolf delboss.
We won't linger on this one,
folks.
There's not much to it,
really.
Remember to punch in, ed.
[Neighs]
- Oh, there is siegfried.
- Over here, roy.
- Hello, siegfried.
- Hello, roy.
Ya ya.
This is a freudian dream.
Hank kimball's brought in.
Hey, mr. Douglas.
See you got a horse.
Well, it's not really a horse.
It's more of a...
Uh, fellas,
this is just wrong.
On the hippodrome track,
high-jumping horses.
Whoo!
Emmett kelly's still eating.
And it's still funny.
[Chuckles]
...with dorothy herbert
blindfolded over
a barrier of fire.
That's blackened beauty,
the cajun horse.
It's c. Everett kook.
...for the funniest prize fight
in circus history.
Bing crosby's relationship
with his son gary
is re-enacted.
[Chuckles like a clown]
Let the nightmare begin.
This is the strangest debate
format I have ever seen.
You know, don't laugh,
but in a way
this is this town's
passion play.
Oh, it's a full-contact who's
afraid of virginia woolf.
Don't talk about that clown,
martha.
- Kitties!
- Meow.
And now clyde beatty
the most fearless man
in all the world,
alone in a cage
with a herd of man-eating
african lions.
The greatest wild animal
trainer of all time.
Is not here.
John turturro?
Hm?
Stella!
The six flying thrillers,
daring mid-air marvels
high over the center ring,
a troupe of absolutely
fearless and unrivalled...
Looks like an ant farm.
Fly through the air,
performing spectacular
and hazardous feats.
I know. You're not going
to complete 5th-grade gym
without doing this, right?
Come on.
Let me hit you on the butt.
- No.
- How about just a light tap?
- Uh-uh, not now.
- Oh, come on, please.
Later it will be
much more fun.
- Guys, stop it.
- You're ruining it for me.
What? What? Sorry.
Pass the word.
Ed's been hitting
the bottle today.
Oh, like that's
a big improvement
over what we've been doing.
Party in susan's dressing room.
[Mutters]
- Uh-oh.
- It's jean allen
with a herd of thunderous
pachyderms,
their trunks
full of new tricks.
A rogue elephant
snaps its tether
and kills a coolie.
Now who's getting dark?
Hoo-hoo.
Like it.
I'm taking this elephant
for a test drive.
Three elephants
and a little lady.
The circus with it's thrills,
fun, sawdust, and spangle
brings joy and merriment
to everyone.
Here comes the circus
is always a memorable event,
a truly great
and carefree day for all
from six to 60.
You think she's working
for peanuts, too?
[Chuckles]
She enjoys this
a little too much.
Um, don't blow
any water right now.
Ah, my favorite part
of the circus.
Oh, wait.
How can something be american
and international?
Let's watch and find out.
Shall we?
Oh, cripes,
I remember that day.
Oh, yeah,
you gotta dress for it.
Oh, yahay, the temperature--
that got all the way down
to about 14 below zero there.
- Oh, yeah.
- You don't know
the half of it.
Earl had to jump start
the chevy that day.
Oh, yahay,
the snow was yay high,
and he come up the back way,
he had to. You know?
Of course I don't know
nothing about that.
Then we seen where
all the schools is closed.
Of course the kids
enjoyed that part.
That was real cold, yeah.
It was just like
the winter of '75,
when it got down to 30 below.
Oh, yeah, but when you
consider the wind chill,
it's when it's about a hundred
below that time.
Oh, joel, you know
it was a good thing I had
the snowmobile suit
for the run over
by evelyn's house there.
Oh, sure. Yep, yep.
It was just so ding dang cold,
I go outside,
the stuff in my nose
just freeze right up.
Ah, yep, yep.
Ah, the scandihoovian sketch.
Yeah.
Oh, yah, squarehead.
Throughout history
people have listened
to the storyteller.
Against their will.
Men who could fashion
myths and fairytales
and make them live
for his listeners.
Sid and marty krofft?
Such men were the brothers
grimm in germany
and hans christian andersen
in denmark,
and such a man
was elias lonnrot in finland.
Here he is on vacation.
This is the story
you are about to see.
Aah!
Phew.
- They're golem.
- Long ago in a faraway place
called kalevala
there was a village
of fisher people.
The land they lived in
was large and beautiful.
As were the women.
...blessed with great rivers
filled with fish,
wonderful forests
with tall trees...
And pollution from the nearby
paper processing plant.
And the people toiled
very hard.
Hey, this is hard.
...and if they worked
the earth and the sea...
Bye, grandma.
...one day they would be given
as their reward...
Is this a documentary?
I'm here for the prince valiant
auditions.
♪♪ [Hums "dueling banjos"]
One, two, three--
I can't fall asleep
counting those guys.
Goats.
Oh.
...and so such was the magic
of the sampo...
The what?
It so happened
that the illmarinen
had a beautiful sister
named annikki...
"Annikki in the u.K."?
Huh.
...and spent her days
happily...
Your mother is long dead.
All the people of the village
loved her dearly
hey, there's bird lancaster.
Walter pidgeon.
Robin givens.
- Chick corea.
- Ooh, good one.
...that would be the sign
that the time had come...
For democracy.
Sampo was to be forged.
Escape to wisconsin.
Ever since annikki
had become a young woman,
she remained by herself
and refused the attention
of any young man
who brazenly thought
he might...
Look at that.
Looks like penny marshall.
...one man she had never met...
Gary bigner.
...for he lived deeper
in the forest.
His name was lemminkainen.
Lime lemminkainen.
He was a woodsman.
He was young and simple.
And practiced slash-and-burn
agriculture.
- He worked hard--
- [all] Ohh!
- ...but was never noticed
at all.
- Whew.
- But there was something
about him that would someday--
- [grunting]
- Oh, there goes the last
spotted owl.
- ...Sooner than anyone thought,
save the village
from the most horrible, cruel
misfortune it would ever know.
- The reagan-bush
administration.
- What these good people
did not realize:
That all the time--
has anyone seen timmy?
Oh, no!
...a witch
plotted against them.
Hey, check it out.
It's sting
and david lee roth
and peter noone
and sammy hagar
and david carradine and...
- Santa?
- Hmm.
Why don't you use an ax
on your hair, you hippie?
For three days,
your mother has not seen you,
lemminkainen.
- Go home and take a rest.
- And take out the garbage,
and help your mother
clean the garage,
for crying out loud.
[Clapping a tune]
♪ From the land
of sky-blue water ♪
♪ water ♪
Hey, check out my log.
I got it for graduation.
[Chuckles]
It's my cigar boat.
[Laughing]
- And a river runs through it.
- Or this.
Hey, get me, I'm making
a mountain dew ad.
♪ Let's go surfin' now,
even sven's learnin' how ♪
♪ if everybody had a spruce tree
across finlandia ♪
♪ I wish they all could be
norwegian girls ♪
♪ they all could be ♪
[Mock foreign accent]
Hey, anybody call a cab?
The adventures
of fjord fairlane.
[Laughter]
Uh-oh. Rush hour.
Now, wait a minute.
Let me get this straight.
Abba's gonna pay me to surf?
John huston's the african log.
White hunter, black heart.
[High-pitched voice]
Damn, crazy swede.
Ancient swedish secret, huh?
♪ My baby takes-- ♪
huh?
Wow. Look at that laundry.
[Mock chuckling]
Hey, I'm gonna go play mini golf
at cross lake.
You wanna go?
She's washing her crystal.
Hmm?
Don't walk on my laundry,
steve.
Yes? May I help you?
- Whose gold is that?
- Mine.
[Lemminkainen]
Can this be the daughter
of the rosy dawn?
[Whispering]
Agent, he's just pulled up
in a log.
[Lemminkainen]
Or the radiance of the moon?
It's not the moon,
nor is it the sun.
I'm just a simple maiden.
You can say that again.
- Annikki is my name.
- Poker's my game.
- Annikki.
- I went to school
with your brother.
Hey, my other log's a redwood.
- [Laughter]
- She's got a gun!
- [All yell]
- Oh.
[Old man's voice]
If you don't like
the way I'm driving,
call 1-800-bite-me.
[Laughs]
[Foreign accent]
Well, it was nice meeting you.
"Lemminkainen," was it?
Eh, whatever.
[Imitating vehicle departing]
That was weird.
Do you want to be finnish?
Sure. We all do.
♪♪ [Humming]
Poppies will make us sleep.
- [Whispering] They're tulips.
- Oh.
[Imitating frogs croaking]
Ah, yes, my little chickadee.
Hey, what's
the pecking order here?
[Laughs]
Eh...
She's got an amazingly
dull life, doesn't she?
[High-pitched voice]
Ah, dinner.
- Oh, no, after you.
- No, after you. I insist.
- No, I insist.
Age before beauty.
- Oh, n--
[imitating yogi bear]
Hey, hello, boo-boo. Mmm.
John irving
wrote the screenplay.
I'm busy.
Annikki.
Sister of mine.
You shaved your beard.
What's the matter?
Oh, my dearest brother.
His eyes sparkle
like the sunlight
glimmering on the sea foam.
[Laughs]
Yes!
And then we swing
back and forth on the highwire
while furiously
spanking each other.
Great! I love it!
It sings. It's got legs.
It's got everything--
listen, you guys.
Please.
Remember I said I'd type in
your ideas for a clown act,
all right?
I find what
we're talking about here
just a little bit derivative
from what we saw the clowns
do in the short.
I think you should
think of your own ideas.
Well, we're not
paying you to think.
Just take all this down
as we dictate it, peggy.
Okay.
Where were we?
Wait. I've got it.
- We're on the trapeze.
- Yep.
And you hang from my tongue.
While I drive sheet-metal
screws into your eyes.
I love it!
It's good.
I admit that.
But maybe we gotta work
more butt into the act.
- Wait, I've got it.
- Yeah?
I grab you and squeeze you
till you hemorrhage--
no, how about I come out
dressed as a suture,
you come out
dressed as an appendix.
A european appendix,
if you know what I mean.
Ooh, very kinky.
Uh, fellas,
can I remind you,
you're gonna be clowns
in a circus.
There's gonna be
kids watching.
Can I just remind you
to bite me?
Now get back to work, della.
Right!
I've got a brilliant idea!
Okay.
This routine
starts out normal,
you and me beating the crap
out of each other.
Then I snap.
I run into the audience
on a homicidal rampage.
Ha ha!
Yes. Then I appear
playing the part of death.
A funny death.
Of course.
Hey, you know what would be
a really funny routine?
What would be really funny?
If we could somehow make
the audience members
question their love
for their spouses.
Yes, and here's the topper.
We convince all the kids
in the audience
that they were adopted!
Ah, ha ha!
Guys, listen.
I knew you would take
something like the circus
and turn it into some dark
carnival of the soul.
Listen, joel,
for your information--
- what the hell?
- Hey!
You didn't take down
a word we said!
You had cambot program
a typing effect.
You were just toying with us,
weren't you?
- That's right.
And you know why?
- Why?
Because there's a little bit
of the clown in all of us.
Good night,
and may god bless.
[Robots scoffing]
- Oh, come on.
I couldn't resist.
- Yeah. Whatever.
This was before unions.
Let it be a lesson to you.
Hey, tom,
could you punch out for me?
[Man shouting]
I'm not going into
early retirement.
Ron wood on
any given morning.
Ooh.
You've come for the fire.
Come on.
A tour's coming through here.
Get to work!
- You've come for the fires.
- Hmm?
How much longer do you
expect me to put up
with your absurd show?
Can't you make the sampo?
You call yourselves wizards!
- Duh...
- We've done the best
we're able to.
- Cast them into
the viper's pit!
- Uh, be unclean, ma'am.
Let the snakes devour him.
Can't you just dock me?
Oh, mistress, I beg of you.
I know someone
who will be able to help you
to build your sampo.
- Who?
- Murray on third shift.
...illmarinen,
in the land of kalevala.
He is the only one
who knows the right way.
You... have long boasted
of your power
over the secrets of nature.
I demand that you
show me now
the face of this illmarinen.
Mmm, let's go check
the files, honey.
[Laughs]
Don't know what I'd do
without my right-hand troll.
Gesundheit.
Illmarinen, come before us.
Illmarinen, stand before us.
- Come before us,
stand before us.
- Oh, they're pentecostal.
Illmarinen, come before us.
- Illmarinen, stand before us.
- Posture.
- He's leaking.
- Illmarinen, come before us.
Illmarinen, stand before us.
- Illmarinen!
- Appear!
Help me, obi-wan.
You're my only help.
Hey, don't sit so close
to the set.
You'll ruin our eyes.
I have fashioned a bracelet
for you.
It's a padlock!
- Annikki?
- No, precious moments.
And she is
illmarinen's sister.
Oh, no way. I thought she was
joanie koslack's brother.
...will be paid
for his pretty sister.
I WONDER WHAT KIND OF NAME
LEMMINKäINEN IS.
Italian? Irish?
♪ LEMMINKäINEN VERY PRETTY ♪
[Laughs]
I made a joke.
Go on swift wings
to the land of kalevala.
Oh, one-hour martinizing.
...to the golden annikki.
When you find her alone,
bring her quickly back
so that she may become
my prisoner!
Oh, she's one sheet
to the wind.
Oh, wait a minute.
I forgot something. Oh!
Grandma's been talking
to the bedding again.
Cuckoo, cuckoo.
You really get a lot of use
out of a good wool cape.
We'll be cruising today
at an altitude
of about 60 feet or so.
Well, let's see.
Now, what did she say?
Go to something
and get something, uh...
- Something.
- [Mutters]
Yeah, please remain seated
until the cape has come
to a complete stop.
- Thank you.
- Hmm?
Oh, don't tell me hercules
is in this movie.
- Hercules is in this movie.
- I asked you not
to tell me that.
♪ Oh, the cabin boy,
the cabin boy ♪
- ♪ the dirty little... ♪
♪♪ [humming]
- [Whispering] No. No.
Hmm?
- Hey, uh, how'd I do that?
- Yeah.
- [Wind howling]
- Boy, kidnapping was real easy
back then.
Oh-ho, popeye!
♪ He's large ♪
♪♪ [humming]
What the hell?
There's a roast in the oven!
I don't know
when I'll be back!
Oh, boy.
The secret storm!
♪ "Da" "veather" started
gettin' rough ♪
♪ the tiny ship "vas" lost ♪
There's a flash flood warning
affecting stonehenge region.
Right.
[Hag voice]
By the pricking of my thumb,
something goofy
this way comes.
[Chuckling]
Come on, dummy.
♪♪ [Humming along
with soundtrack]
Geez, thanks for the lift.
Call the front desk
if you need anything.
[Laughs]
I got one!
Hey, get me. I'm swedish,
and I've got rhythm.
♪ I sing whenever I sing ♪
[Laughing]
- Illmarinen!
- It's 3:00 in the morning!
The evil witch louhi
has stolen your sister.
Yeah? And?
- Annikki?
- Yes.
Here. Wait a minute.
Let me put my sword out.
There.
Give me the sword.
I will go to pohjola.
Ah, let me just finish up here.
So there.
Say hi to my sister.
I WILL GO WITH YOU TO POHJOLA,
LEMMINKäINEN.
Wait. I'll drive.
Let me get my keys.
Yep. There we go.
♪♪ [humming]
Vainamoinen,
my sister has been stolen--
- well, was she insured?
- ...By the evil witch louhi.
- Looks kind of like
a bible story.
- Yeah.
Tell us how we can find our way
to the mystery shores
of pohjola.
- Go down to
the third stoplight, and...
- All the way
to the edge of the world.
- And if you want to go there--
- take the santa monica freeway.
...you must build a boat which
will carry you over the waves
like a white swan.
Tell us, vainamoinen,
how can we build a boat
such as that?
I'm glad you asked.
I'm having
a boat-building seminar.
In this ancient oak tree,
you will find your boat.
You have but to take it out,
and it will carry you
across the sea
to the shores of pohjola.
Okay, how much is this
gonna set me back?
Oh, I'm chafin' like me.
[Laughs]
Oops. I did it again.
You kidding me?
A boat in here?
It's a chip-away game.
Is there another wise man
we could talk to?
Eight years later...
[Chuckling]
So, anyway, that's what
really got me interested
in stamp collecting.
Of course,
I've always loved the theater.
Just shut up.
[Mock grunting]
Hey, no boat.
That's my scratching tree,
you jerks.
Uh, not that tree.
- [Snickers]
- Uh, fred, did I mention
that I have a boat?
- Sorry.
- No.
Oh, now they're
just showing off.
Oh, now, what did they
chop the sail out of?
- Oh, they cut the wood
real thin. Really.
- Uh-huh.
May the sun light the way
to bring you safely home again.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Can the balloon juice, gramps.
We're outta here.
Hey, shouldn't we patch
the bottom first?
I just pray there aren't
no portages.
- Oh, boy.
- The stay puft marshmallow man
in chains?
Kinky.
It's giant sweetbreads.
It's body wars.
Someone has come to visit us!
Quick, pick up the place,
make yourself presentable!
- [Male voice] Where?
- [Male voice #2] Over here.
- Near me.
- What, it's a bag
of homer simpsons?
- Who are you?
- [Female voice] We are winds.
Wait. One at a time, please.
Come on.
- --The wind?
- [Female voice] Yes.
I am the south wind.
Do you provide a service
of some sort?
[Male voice]
I am the west wind.
[Male voice #2]
And i-- I am the east wind.
Put your teeth in!
I can't understand you!
Are you the north wind?
[Male voice #3]
No. I am the mist.
I'm relative humidity.
It's not so much the heat
as it is me.
♪ I'm the summer wind
come blowin' in ♪
♪♪ [humming]
- And you-- which one are you?
- [Mock chuckling]
Oh, me?
I'm just the laundry.
[Male voice #4]
I am the north wind.
- Call me sandy.
- I was born among
the ice floes.
Oh, that's fine, thank you.
[Chuckling]
[North wind]
Please let me out.
Yeah, I didn't ask
for a biography.
Very well.
I will let you out.
So, this is where I find you,
my little pet.
Um, we weren't kissing.
We were just talking.
Perhaps you need
something to amuse you.
Just come with me.
I'll find something
for you to do.
I've got one of those
little pool tables
I bought at brookstone.
- You'll love it.
- Throw my prisoner in chains!
All right!
Some orders we like to get.
[Chuckling]
- [Shouting]
- Yeah.
Deep thoughts.
Oh, walleye chop.
I'd better get out there.
Erik's small cigars.
Inconceivable.
They're gaining on us.
- Oh, the keg's here.
- Ah, he's come,
as I said he would.
Do you see his boat
approaching our shore?
Do you hear the waves
bringing him nearer?
Come. Wake up.
Run to the beach
and welcome him.
You're the boss.
You're the queen of everything.
Okay.
Smiles, everyone! Smiles!
[Chuckles]
Eh...
Hey, do you have a dock
or something?
We'd really appreciate it!
[Chuckles]
Look at that boat.
- What, did you carve it
out of a tree?
- Shut up! Shut up!
Boat.
Mistress, oh, you were right.
The boat
is bringing lemminkainen--
- mmm! [Smacking lips]
- ...And his friend,
the immortal
blacksmith illmarinen.
- Greetings for all!
- Hi.
Who accepts the challenge
that I have brought?
- Nope. Can't. Got a bad knee.
- I did the last challenge.
I have come to free
the maiden annikki.
- I am here with her brother.
- Uh, tony.
- You are no coward? Then fight!
- Noel coward?
If your power
can protect you from my arrow.
Yes, my power is great.
Uh, it's not that fun
going to grandma's anymore.
Magic and charms
and terrible spells--
enough to drive you back
into the boiling home
from which you come,
you blundering fool.
That's enough of that.
You imagine we've come here
to listen to
an old woman raving?
- That's why most people come.
- Now, do you accept
the challenge,
or will you give up
my sister without it?
- Take the curtain.
- Go for the box.
I will not give up annikki.
- ...bust the witch's bosom.
- No, wait!
- Let me take off my girdle.
- Wait now!
I will give
your maiden back to you
if you perform
two simple tasks for me.
- Aw, this bites. Let's blow.
- What are they?
Pick up my dry cleaning
and call the vet.
I have a field
overrun with snakes,
and he must first plow it.
- All right.
- It's weird, but...
- Tell me where your field is.
- Come on.
COME ON, GOOD LEMMINKäINEN.
Don't wait up, erik,
if you know what I mean.
- Say, that is cold.
- [Laughs]
You see it before you.
I see an el greco.
[Louhi]
A field of snakes.
Hey, kevin costner's
in that, isn't he?
- No, this is the dirty version.
- Oh.
I want a plow, and I must have
a powerful horse with it.
Hey,
I'm the curse boss here.
...to feed one of my horses
to those snakes?
Needs a horse.
I will build him a horse.
I'll make it out of a tree.
Uh--oh.
Horse chestnut.
[Laughs]
Oh, mistress.
Don't call me that
in public.
You must not allow illmarinen
to build that horse.
He'll be sure to plow the field,
and they will take annikki.
And illmarinen will refuse
to make us a sampo.
Have patience.
He won't be able
to carry her away.
Now, slip into that
stable boy suit
and meet me later
down by the [whispers].
[Laughs]
Yes, mistress. Oh, my.
Ooh. Uh-oh.
Wow.
And the sculling crew
takes to the lake.
We've got to get
organized.
Attica! Attica! Attica!
It's the oslo riots.
Hey, uh, that's not very smart
when you're in the boat.
He's pounding
the air there.
It's an air hammer.
[Laughter]
Hey, we're goin' over
to sven's after, huh?
Want to?
Huh?
Suddenly it's flashdance.
♪ He's a steel town's fan
on a saturday night ♪
Weird.
Okay. Okay.
If he can make a horse,
why'd he have to cut
that tree down?
Mm.
Yeah, well,
now I just sit back
and rake in the praise,
pretty much.
Hello, daddy.
[Laughs]
The tristar logo's ready.
He's...
Safe.
♪ They ran callin'
wildfire ♪
♪ whoo ♪
Ouch. Phew. Stingy.
That's still hot.
Hello.
I'm from the temp agency.
I'm your horse
for the day.
Oh. Speed the plow.
Hey, good timing.
Boy, we work good together.
Could you rub some solarcaine
on me, please?
A horse.
We didn't plan on that.
Would someone please
turn the wagner off?
Hey, I think he just
invented the mobil logo.
Oh. Neat.
♪ Doo doo doo doo doo
doo doo doo doo doo ♪
Ew.
Yech.
Snakies.
It's kind of a goofy,
scandinavian double-dare.
[Laughs]
Oh, man.
It's a puppet. Look.
He's being attacked
by a woozle.
[Laughs]
Yeah, they're--they're all
yellin' "fake." Ha!
And now I'd like to do my
nastassja kinski impression.
I'll just take
off my clothes.
[Laughs]
I knew they'd "worm"
their way into the film.
[Laughs]
Worm--
snakes.
You know, I wonder if that horse
comes in any other colors.
Uh, he's the enemy,
but you gotta admire him.
Yup. Yup.
Tip your cap.
Uh, pretty much.
Get a look at this,
huh?
Now, let's go in and see
if mom's got dinner ready.
Oh, great.
We can plant more snakes now.
[Laughs]
All right.
I've finished plowing
your field.
Planted now with care.
[Grunts]
And may the grain grow
as high as my shoulder.
Now, where is she?
We want to take her back.
I'll give you
your annikki.
But it won't
do you much good.
There isn't very much left
of your boat.
D'oh--hey.
That's below the belt.
Yeah, I don't really get
witches' humor.
Mm-mm.
Come along.
Let me show you.
Brother.
She's got issues, huh?
Mm.
It's the swedish dells.
The ducks. Ride the ducks.
Hey. You wrecked our boat
you freaked-out maniac.
A great fish
was swimming near the shore.
Uh-huh.
It flipped its tail once
and smashed your boat.
Well I supposed those
kind of things ha--what?
...i will make a new boat.
An iron one.
And tell your fish
if he tries to smash this one
it'll break his teeth off.
Well,
you don't have to yell.
Huh? What?
They're roasting
bullwinkle.
[Gasps]
No.
Save me, rocky.
Help me.
Again?
Oh, nobody ever helps
this guy.
Look! A boat!
Wuh-oh.
Outta control.
[Gasps]
What's going to become
of us now?
Oh, everything's about you,
isn't it?
When log flume rides
go horribly wrong.
You may get burnt
on this ride.
[Screams]
Uh, there's a flaming moose
blocking traffic
on i-35 w northbound.
Would somebody
please put me out?
I seem to be on fire.
Protect us.
Have mercy, dear mistress.
Chase it away.
Do something.
Now, there's something
you don't see everyday,
chauncey.
Uh, what's that, edgar?
Kiss goin' bass fishin'.
Huh.
Quite a boat,
wouldn't you say?
Now that it's finished,
we'll be on our way
the minute you
give us annikki.
I demand that you
make your boat stop.
When you release my sister.
Your only excuse before
was because
your fish raked
our other boat.
Ugh, point well taken.
You act like
I'm the bad guy.
I don't know if your sister
is ready for that.
She's still
upstairs dressing.
...lady of pohjola.
You better give us annikki.
Only he has performed well
what I gave him to do.
And you.
What did you do?
Yeah.
I've heard you
make magic too.
Hell,
I made the horse.
What are you
talking about?
What magic?
I mean,
the sampo.
♪ Dun dun dun ♪
You'll forge a sampo.
Or you'll never see the face
of your pretty sister again.
Can we see
the other parts?
Ugh, criminy.
Better look up "sampo" quick.
I think she's serious.
Only a sampo.
No, tom. You're thinking
of a "sample."
S-a-m-p-l-e. We're talking
about sampo with an "o."
Oh.
Okay. Okay. Okay.
So if a sampo
isn't a small taste
of no-fat cheese
at the grocery store,
then what,
I implore you, is it?
Well, I was thinking
that maybe a sampo
is really good
can opener.
No. I think it's
a strapless evening gown.
You think everything
is a strapless evening gown.
I just think
they're neat is all.
What do you think,
joel?
Uh, I think
a sampo's like
a hand-hammered conch belt
with turquoise inlays,
used to accentuate
an oversized blouse?
I think it's that dent
between the nose and lip.
Well, whatever it is, that witch
wants it more than anything.
So, it must be some sort
of wrinkle cream.
Oh, no.
I got it.
Sampo--a progressive,
new corporation
with an eye towards
the future.
Sampo is a corporation
for people, by people.
I think it increases
corn yields.
I think it's a nasty, little,
rubber novelty item.
You know what I mean?
Well,
maybe it's not tangible.
I mean, maybe sampo is found
in the laughter of children,
or in the roar
of the tide,
or in the capacity
to love and be loved.
No, I know.
I think sampo is a new
high-energy prop comic.
You know, like, "ladies and
gentlemen,
"the funny bone is proud to
present--
funny man, sampo."
Well, one thing's for sure
gentlemen--
the u.s. of a. Still makes
the best damn sampos
on the market,
and I mean nobody
is gonna change that.
I--I've got it.
It--it's fresh.
It's sassy.
It's free. It's me.
It's an exciting,
new fragrance
by prince matchabelli.
[Laughs]
Uh, no, um...
Well, to be honest,
everybody,
we don't know
what a sampo is.
Not a clue.
If you know
what a sampo is,
write in on a piece of paper,
throw it away
and then
try not to think about it.
You'll be glad you did.
Sampo.
Whoa. Oh, no.
We got movie sign.
Let's go.
Ding. Sampo up.
Oh, geez.
What a day. Ugh.
You know, I really admire
how you stood firm
on the sampo issue,
your witchy-ness.
You didn't give an inch
and I really admire
that quality.
We'd like to show you, uh, how
we maximize warehouse,
uh, to increase
sampo shipments.
[Laughs]
It's really exciting.
I think you should
come along
and take a look
at what we're doing.
Well?
I must have
a wisp of lamb's wool,
a feather from a swan,
and a barleycorn.
Ya hear this guy?
Get him the smallest
of the flock.
And a swan.
And a whole bushel
of barley.
And some mini doughnuts.
Um, can we get married?
We're in love.
Nobody asked for a goose.
You take that right away.
Hmm?
Oh, now somebody's sweater's
gonna have a big flaw.
You put your feather
in before the wool?
Hmm.
With this wool
will I clothe you.
With these teeth
will you bite me.
With this barley
will I nourish you.
Oh. He's making
chex party mix.
Oh.
Ladies and gentlemen--
the magic
of ulysses s. Grant.
...desired--the sampo.
Sampo.
"Sampo" means "flavor."
Now give me the fire
that burned in the clouds.
Huh?
How dare you.
Don't mention that.
It's dirty.
You want the sampo?
That is the only fire
I can forge it in.
It has to be
the heavenly flame.
Is it hot in here?
I wonder if this
is some trick
to deprive me
of the heavenly fire.
[Grunts]
But we won't have much use
for that if he makes the mill.
Give him the fire.
We'll be able to have
as much flour as we want
without grain.
And we'll be able
to have salt.
And we will be able
to make silver and gold.
Oh, let him have it.
Oh, please.
My spin doctors.
Go and fetch the heavenly flame
for him then.
But someone stay here
to answer the phones.
Boy, she's really broken through
the glass ceiling, huh?
Oh, yeah.
♪ Dum dum dum dum dum dum
dum dum dum dum dum ♪
♪ dum dum dum
dum dum dum ♪
Um, yesterday's soup.
We're trying to get rid of it.
Mm. Kinda looks
like caligula in here.
How would you know that?
The soup has a escort?
[Laughs]
Good soup.
[Grunts]
Here. Ditch this
flamin' skull for me.
I don't know how
that got in there.
Nice weight.
Mm-hmm.
Real good flame.
Nice.
Put all your
idle people to work.
I'll need there help.
Tell them to work
the bellows.
You heard what he said.
Saul bellows.
Get to work.
No, no.
Oh.
[Laughs]
Is it sampo yet?
[Grunts]
Now, be careful.
This plate is very hot.
So, how does this work?
Hey, let me know
when you need a break.
Mark vii.
Mark vii, damn it.
Oh, mark vii. Whew.
Freedom trolls.
Working for you.
Where's a friggin' sampo...
[Scoffs]
Uh, steve, honey?
Why don't you go get
daddy a beer.
You said you'd make the mill.
Where is it?
Your men can't
make the fire hot enough.
Sure.
Blame my department.
Get working,
you slackards.
Ooh.
Pump the bellows.
Make the flames leap up.
We're doing our best,
mistress.
He's got
a cocktail dress on.
Ah, it's not done.
Must have been frozen
in the middle.
He's got
delusions of grandeur.
Hey, it's like
urban cowboy.
[Laughs]
[Servo groans]
Boy, how's that beer
coming, stevie?
Work harder!
Get the seed out!
- Faster! Faster!
- Get off, todd, come on,
I'm serious!
They think I'm working,
that's the beauty part.
Oh, I hate this
infernal routine.
♪ Burn, baby, burn ♪
♪ disco inferno ♪
Oh, the guy on top
must be the shop steward.
Ah.
Will someone please
get the phone?
Kids come running for
the rich taste of sampo.
Mm.
[All]
Ow!
Be careful,
that's nitric acid.
We don't have very much.
[All]
Ow!
I hate this
school lunch program.
Water's considered
a vegetable.
Ugh, this is why
I don't make sampos
- except on holidays.
- Hey, can we help?
Uh, you can help
by setting the table.
Oh.
Sorry, sampo's off.
Sampo...
Ask for it by name.
- Sampo.
- Ask for it by name.
Yeah. That's a sampo, huh?
Sampo.
Ray nitschke?
You get wafers with it!
No, you don't get
any wafers with it!
- I said I would.
- It's very impressive,
but how do I know it works?
Well, you just plug it
into the wall outlet
and turn it on.
Let there be gold
and flour!
And salt!
Of course, I recommend
the service contract.
[Men murmur]
Still, I think it would
look better by the couch.
Sorry I doubted your sampo.
Mm. [Smacks lips]
Boy, I thought
there'd be more people
around the gold part
of this thing,
but the line's really
not that long, you know?
This is what it would've been
like if perot would've won.
[Servo chuckles]
Oh, great, rock salt!
We'll never slip
on the driveway again.
Makes you think,
don't it, honey?
Nice to see 'em so happy.
Gold.
Uh, the manual's in the box.
And the first upgrade's free.
Now give us back annikki.
- Oh, she's home already.
- All right.
I will give your pretty sister
back to you now.
I must warn you,
she's aged some.
Wait, that's
the wrong sister.
Grab yourself a heaping
helping of sweet annikki.
[Servo chuckles]
- Annikki.
- Do I know you?
- Lemminkainen.
- You're not as cute
as I remember.
♪ On a clear day... ♪
Annikki.
My little sister.
Take that creature
away from my palace!
- Oh, killjoy.
- After what she's done
with all those
nasty flowers.
Come on.
Don't worry, lady,
we're outta here.
Gah.
Well, hey, missus,
the sampo stopped working,
and we didn't get
the service contract.
Smash it and take them away.
And I want them
all inventoried, too!
I don't want them here--
man, I wonder what her
meyers-briggs test was like.
How were you ever able
to rescue me
- from that wicked creature?
- Well, I had to make
this boat all by myself.
Hey, leave my sister alone.
Your brother, illmarinen,
made a sampo
and left it with
the wicked witch
- in place of you.
- A sampo?
You mean, one of those
big things that makes
- gold and salta and stuff?
- Yeah.
You mean the new '92 sampo
with the leather interior?
It's because of me.
He deprived our people
of their rightful treasure.
I am returning to pohjola,
and I shall
recover the sampo.
No, illmarinen.
I am going back for it now.
Oh, well, I think
a better plan
would be to go back
and get supplies--
- hey!
- Hey, he's got pure wool on!
He's gonna shrink right up!
Try the cleaning power
of new lemon-kainnen
in your rinse cycle.
This is it, isn't it?
Uh-huh. I think so.
Ugh, really love
the new sampo.
No buyer's remorse here,
witchie-poo.
Who's hungry for salt?
Oh, jeez,
I'd better plan this.
Let's see. [Clears throat]
Uh, gotta take the sampo.
It's my dad's.
No, no, damn.
Sampo repair.
No, no, might I just pop in
and grab my sampo?
No! Darn. Ugh.
Oh, no, they really like it.
I was hoping they wouldn't be
getting into the sampo.
No such luck.
Mm, a good heft.
I caught you,
you filthy wretch,
trying to steal my gold!
- I wasn't!
- Catch him!
Don't let him get away!
Find him and throw him
into the--
hey, tony, come on, it's me!
Your roommate!
- Monkey-pile.
- Ooh.
- Pew! Ugh,
that was a mistake.
- [Joel coughs]
That was
the chili relleno wind.
Ew!
Ooh, ouch.
Who let the mist out?
It blinds me
so I cannot see.
- [Servo coughs]
- Back into my bag
mist, come back to me.
Back into thy bag.
Why did thee
even have the mist
if it bugs thee so much?
It's kind of like a giant
neosynephrine bag.
- Isn't it?
- [Men mutter]
Gone!
Ma'am?
Where is the many-colored
dome of the sampo?
Ma'am, the dome is an option
that you did not order.
Go after him
and bring him back here!
I can never just sit back
and enjoy my sampo.
[Men strain]
Hey! It's nice out here.
Ah, there he is.
Miss america!
Destroy lemminkainen's boat!
Release them!
Let the winds rush forth
to destroy this thief.
Fly, monkeys! Fly!
[Crow cackles]
Oh, now why does this happen
at 4:30 on a friday?
- Gah.
- ♪ lemminkainen boat ♪
♪ exciting and new ♪
Aguirre, the wrath of god.
I'm gonna get
a bigger boat, right?
Yeah, we're gonna get
a bigger boat, definitely.
Make the witch a sampo.
What the heck
was I thinking, anyway?
Wind, with matthew modine
and jennifer grey.
Now on video.
Hey, it looks just like
the statue of iwo jima,
if you cross your eyes and get
the poles with those guys--
well.
Hold on, buck! Hold onto
the boat, bucky!
Anybody got any dramamine?
- No.
- [Crow retches]
Ladies and gentlemen,
the swedish moses of soul.
♪ There's got to be ♪
♪ a morning after ♪
The boat is wrecked!
Don't get short with me!
- D'oh!
- [Louhi cackles]
Yeah, right,
madonna and her dancers
get along really good.
Uh, still can't let go
of the sampo, can you?
Let it go, sven.
Um, dad said
I could use the car.
You got the keys?
He will be coming home soon.
And I promise you,
I will dance with you
at your wedding feast.
Eh, give me
the good news now.
Our father, who art-- huh?
[Women sob]
Your brave son lemminkainen
has met his death.
- Huh?
- That can't be true.
My son lives.
Cuckoo, cuckoo, cuckoo.
Ooh, she is off the beam.
- I see a kidney.
- Oh.
I do, there.
Heathcliff!
Catherine!
Have pity on
a mother's prayer.
Friend of the four winds
of heaven--
- um, have we met?
- Can you tell me
what has become
of my brave son?
I have troubles enough
of my own, old woman.
The men strip my bark
for making baskets.
The children break
my branches for brooms.
How should I know
anything about your son?
Jeez, sorry I asked.
Birch, birch, birch.
Now get out of my office.
Miss jenkins, I pay you
to screen these people.
I see a past president
who shall remain nameless.
- Oh, you mean?
- Chester arthur.
Hey, uh, lady?
I'm a nice big pine
that you could
pray to, maybe. Maybe.
Tell me, oh wandering road.
Have pity on
a poor mother's sorrow.
Do you know what happened
- to my son?
- Uh...
Oh...I'll put the word out
on the street.
Oh, I am the street.
Excuse me, I'm kind of
stuck in a rut.
Mother teresa, in a role
that will inspire you.
You should have pity on me.
I am the road.
Uh, I didn't appreciate
what kerouac said about me.
--Find your wandering son.
Oh, poor road--
you have everything!
I have nothing!
I have enough troubles
of my own.
Now I know what they mean
when they say
the road goes on forever.
--How many times men
have trampled on--
she's praying to county road
d-2, what does she want?
How they make
the hooves of their horses
kick me...
What is it with
the inanimate objects today?
Have you thought about
praying to me?
God? The big g-meister?
Dear almighty
refrigerator door--
oh.
Oh, glorious sun.
You who look over all.
- Well, I do my best.
- Answer a mother's prayer.
Tell me where
I can find my son,
my brave boy.
Look for your son...
She's praying
to a mills brother.
Far in the north...
In the cold...
And craggy land...
Of pohjola.
You should do voice-overs.
-- A prisoner of the evil
witch louhi.
At least, he was
as of last wednesday.
It's a richard diebenkorn
painting.
I think.
Oh, great north
deciduous forest.
Ah, never mind.
Ever eat a pine tree?
Many parts are edible.
[Servo hums]
What? Hey!
Somebody took my minnows.
Oh, I think I'll just
skip some rocks.
Oh, dead, bloated carp,
floating in the shallow--
- ugh.
- Hey, it looks
like one of those
hamm's beer clocks.
Sea wheat.
It's...
[Imitates fanfare]
I hate mondays.
Now wipe your feet
before you come into finland.
[Imitates groaning]
Morning.
♪ This small mound is alive ♪
♪ with the sound of ♪
When lemminkainen
met annikki.
♪ I pick myself up
I dust myself off ♪
♪ I start the deal
over again ♪
I can't believe it.
I'm david mccallum.
Lemminkainen!
No, I didn't get
your flippin' sampo.
Lemminkainen.
Oh, my son.
Way to wreck the scene, mom.
Forgive me, dearest mother.
And you should forget me.
Okay.
I have no right to be happy,
for I have destroyed the sampo.
Jerk.
Hey!
- Hey!
- Where's the sampo?
- How's that sampo look?
- We're excited about the sampo.
Oh.
I just wanted to hear
"I went with the sampo," is all.
How's the sampo?
An ashtray?
Give me my sister back.
Here, I...
Got one of these already.
Sampo is no more.
Well, I did bring
the sampo home game.
Be of good cheer,
brave knight.
Hey, you're the road,
aren't you?
You, my people,
take heart.
We've hit bottom.
...as you will see,
even this,
a fragment of the sampo
will bring
much joy and happiness
to the people of kalevala.
Oh, a lot of good
that does them now.
Ugh.
Kalevala, come before us.
Kalevala,
come before us.
Kalevala, come before us.
Kalevala,
stand before us.
This is my favorite bit he does.
Watch this. It's good.
Good mistress. Come quickly.
Something's coming in
on the urine scope, sir.
The evil lemminkainen
lives yet.
Oh,
you got some on my robe.
Now let my cloak bear me
far to kalevala.
To destroy the people
who live there.
It's the von trapps!
Yeah,
out for their morning run.
Huzzah, everyone.
Did you hear there is no sampo?
Yeah, it's really too bad.
No sampo, eh?
Bummer.
Let us be gay,
for he is a...
I'm so glad
it's a dry celebration.
It's so much more fun
than the kegger would have been.
♪ Failed to bring back
the sampo ♪
♪ we shall die of starvation ♪
♪ sampo ♪
What is this?
Stalag 17 the musical?
I think
it's the black oak arkansas.
♪ Failure, failure,
such a failure ♪
♪ failure, failure,
what a really failure ♪
Hey, it's ravi shankar.
♪ Failure, failure ♪
Surrender, ilsa!
♪ Failure, failure... ♪
Recon! Look out!
[Imitates engine]
I meant to do that.
Marty feldman in a role
that won't surprise you.
♪ Failure ♪
♪ failure ♪
Well, looks like
rutherford b. Hayes
just got out of the sauna.
♪ Stupid,
stupid little failure ♪
Ah, hand over the bride.
I can't wait all day.
Well, here's the keys.
Uh, she's a little slow
to start in the winter.
Just give her some gas.
Wait, my dear.
Just wait till you see
the gift I brought for you.
Oh, I guess they shouldn't
have registered in hell.
♪ We still think
he's a failure ♪
What? She's marrying
the yale crew team?
Bad news.
They want to water-ski.
Our own slave ship?
You shouldn't have.
Hurry up.
They're gonna consummate.
All right. Hit it.
[Imitates engine]
Hey, the kids look ripe.
'Bout ready to drop.
Plump.
It's a nice day
for a wet wedding.
- [Laughter]
- Oh, and, you know,
the kids planned the wedding
all by themselves,
and I think they've done
such a nice job.
We're just so lucky that
the rain held out, you know.
Um, I thought
we were gonna get a limo.
Sure beats fooling around
in a nice hotel, eh, honey?
Come on. Kiss him.
♪ Here comes the failure ♪
You know, this is considered
a riot in scandinavia.
[Laughs]
Wild.
♪ He's a failure,
la, la, la ♪
♪ what a loser,
♪ total failure,
total failure ♪
♪ failure, failure, la ♪
You know,
this is the kind of music
that "up with people"
rejected.
♪ Failure, la, la, la ♪
Oh, they're gonna honeymoon
at a rest stop?
♪ Total failure,
a total failure ♪
- [All] ♪ failure, failure ♪
- ♪ la, la, la ♪
Okay, that's fine.
Please disperse.
♪ Failure, utter failure ♪
♪ he's a loser and a chump ♪
♪ failure, failure,
a total failure ♪
♪ what a loser ♪
Okay.
Oh, that's for fun.
Uh, are you with the bride
or the failure?
Huh. Check out this guy.
He looks like something
you'd buy in a gift shop
up north.
[Chuckles]
Now why's he wearing
a hershey's kiss on his head?
Hey. Is that--?
- Brando's here.
- It's brando!
Hey, it's brando!
Hi, mr. Brando.
All rise.
Santa is entering the lodge.
What the hell
is going on in here?
This is my room.
Uh, just throw this
on the gift table, would you?
Didn't have time
to wrap it.
Here you go.
They never invite me
to anything!
May health and happiness
be with you
all the days of your life.
- Oh, no.
- He's drunk.
Health be with you,
vainamoinen.
You are kind to pay a visit
to our humble little cottage.
Oh, thanks.
I see this coming in real handy.
[Laughs]
What am I? I'm a moose.
Grandpa,
that's aunt essy's urn!
[Imitates spitting, coughing]
Your beer is almost too strong
for an old man like me.
Ugh. Coronary. Ugh.
It's the jolly troll.
Hmm?
Oh, she's calling
the batman.
Hmm. Maybe she's mad
'cause she used to date
lemminkainen, and...
Yeah, she's lots of laughs,
but not the kind
you'd settle down with.
She's fine for junior year,
but you gotta move on.
Ooh.
[Child screams]
♪ That was the night ♪
♪ that the lights
went out in finland ♪
- [Evil laughter]
- Oh, looks like she's
dragging a muffler there.
Evil times have fallen
on happy kalevala.
Come on. It's just
a circuit breaker, grandpa.
She's stolen the sun.
Golly, he's really calm
in a crisis.
Hi.
Sorry about the failure.
Fair well, good friend.
Fair the well,
kind mistress.
Fair the well.
Thank you.
Uh, I had the cut-crystal bowl
that the dip was in.
Uh, well, we'll come back.
[Scoffs]
Great wedding.
Get half a buzz on, and then
sent home with a torch.
There can be no happiness
without the sun.
Oh, come on, kirsten.
I'm a night person. I love it.
Keep for me my kantale.
Take a hit if you want to.
Now it can only remain silent.
I must not play on it
unless the sun is up.
Oh, mr. Particular.
Everything's
gotta be just right.
Yeah, looks like
they're trying
to take back the night
over there.
- Oh, I think
it's a melanie concert.
- Oh.
Ladies and gentlemen,
presenting,
in her one-woman show,
gypsy.
Here we go.
- Shh.
- Oh, sorry.
♪ There's a big frontier
out there called life ♪
♪ I ain't nobody's daughter ♪
♪ I ain't nobody's wife ♪
♪ I'm gonna stake
my very own claim of land ♪
♪ and you're gonna
wanna know who I am ♪
♪ I'm gypsy ♪
♪ gypsy rose me ♪
♪ gypsy rose not you ♪
♪ not you ♪
♪ or you ♪
♪ gypsy rose ♪
♪ me ♪
♪ yay ♪
All right.
Gypsy, yay!
[Applause]
Oh, thank you very much.
You know,
we're all traveling.
You, me, that little gold guy
over there.
We're traveling
on the big trip of life,
and sometimes it turns out
we haven't packed
the right clothes
for our own personal journey.
Oh.
I've been struggling
to make ends meet.
The social worker
stopped by today.
We'll get by. Somehow.
Thank you!
Thank you very much.
So moving.
I'm sick of fighting with you,
boyfriend.
But I'm not going
to walk out that door.
No, sir.
I'm going to run out that door.
- [Applause]
- Thank you.
Thank you very much.
- She's a survivor.
- Yeah, you bet.
You know,
I've seen her before.
Hey, is my act interfering
with your conversation, buddy?
[Laughter]
Okay,
three guys together, huh?
What? Some sort of
love connection screw up?
[Laughter]
Thank you.
Oh, thank you, thank you.
What a night, everybody.
But before I go, I wanna
tell you a little story.
A story about a gal...
Who ran the higher functions
of a little satellite
in a synchronous orbit.
A gal that everyone thought
was perhaps a little slow,
a little naive,
a little simple.
But let me tell you something
about that gal.
She had spirit,
she had guts,
and most of all,
she had a huge heart.
That gal was on her journey,
and when her luggage ended up
on another planet,
that gal picked herself up,
dusted herself off,
and wore the same outfit
two days in a row.
That plucky little gal
is me.
Oh, thank you very much.
[Applause]\
oh, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
We've got commercial sign.
I'll be right back.
I'm don ameche.
I'll be here all week.
Thank you.
Hey, look! It's skylab.
- [Whistling]
- [Servo whistles]
Hey, mommy's back,
and I've got presents!
Now, open the bag
and release the blizzard!
May the north wind
bring snow
to blanket the land
of kalevala
forever!
And may you stay
forever, yah!
Meanwhile, in frostbite falls,
minnesota.
We have some
school closings today,
including stockholm,
public and private.
Oslo, public and parochial.
Helsinki vo-tech,
suomi junior high.
- Boy, that looks cold.
- Mm-hmm.
[Servo scats
"ride of the valkyries"]
Pamplona, spain. The annual
running of the goats!
[Bots baa]
The christmas
that almost wasn't.
It's not a fit night out
for man or beast.
The day the earth became
unseasonably cool.
I guess everybody's
going to blame me
for this, too.
Yeah...what?
Oh, I thought
I caulked that thing.
Looks like they moved in
with the ingalls family.
Yeah, little house
on the tundra.
[Servo laughs]
Jeez. Has to have
half and half
with her coffee.
Okay, dear, I'll wade
through the blizzard
to get your half and half.
The shining.
Actually, it looks
kind of inviting.
♪ Moonlight in vermont ♪
♪ I'm gonna bury gary ♪
♪ in a pile of snow ♪
[Servo hums]
Ah, jeez,
one little cup of coffee,
and she's gotta have
her friggin' half and half.
[Servo grumbles]
♪ Walking in my
winter underwear ♪
[Servo chuckles]
Hey, a penny.
♪ Watch out
where the huskies go ♪
♪ and don't you eat
that yellow snow ♪
Uh, hey, aunt rody?
The old grey goose
is dead.
Rosebud.
Rip taylor's outside.
Come on! I wanna come in!
'Cause it's cold outside!
Hah! I got a big prop
I wanna show you!
It's funny!
It's true.
First day of marriage
is the hardest.
Hey, here's
your damn dinner.
Hmm, I suppose you want me
to clean that now.
I'm not the pheasant
plucker.
I'm the pheasant
plucker's son.
I'm only plucking
pheasants
till the pheasant
plucker comes.
I know, dear. I know.
Um... not on the good bench.
Honey, it's a swan's
unfrozen dinner.
- [Crow laughs]
- Oh, what's the use?
We'll call her trudy.
Wait, she's wearing
an embroidery hoop
on her head.
One word. Annulment.
I'm afraid the poor thing
is dead.
Oh, the sampo
could've saved it.
Shut up with that sampo!
Soon we will all
be like this poor bird.
[Servo groans]
She's turning into
a steak on legs.
I can't even see
your eyes, annikki.
Without thinking olives.
That's the worst thing
about this twilight.
You're in the house.
Take your bike helmet off.
I can't even remember
what color they are.
Let me look
in your eyes again.
Look, she's swedish.
I'm guessing they're blue.
[Annikki sobs]
Yeah? Well, I'm gonna eat.
Honey, we got any
orange sauce in the house?
Duck... with orange.
Duck with cherry.
A duck surprise.
Duck without
orange or cherry.
Illmarinen!
Hey, what's the deal
with your sister, man?
- Illmarinen.
- D'ah-- hamburgers!
Oh, sorry, dozed off
on the old anvil.
- This--
- sucks.
- Cannot go on much longer.
You must make
a new sun for us.
I'll use the sampo
to make one.
Oh, wait, we don't have one.
That's right.
I will do what I can.
Not as I do.
Huh. Grandpa rioted
and got a week in the hole.
The great escape,
30 years later.
[Servo hums great escape theme]
[Crow yawns]
Well, I'm turning in.
Big day.
[All]
♪ fa-hoo fores ♪
♪ da-hoo dores ♪
♪ welcome... ♪
Why are they so bummed out?
Oh, they just
saw captain ron.
Oh.
Personally,
I like kurt russell.
I loved the computer
wore tennis shoes,
but that's just me.
No, no, the sun's bigger.
Yes, we recall
it being quite large.
And it's got--
it's got spots.
- Mm-hmm.
- Yes.
What're you doing,
illmarinen?
He is forging
a new sun for us.
- This is futile.
- No, it's fusion.
Trying to forge
the sun anew?
The one thing left
is to release it from prison.
Well then, you come up
with your own ideas, man.
Take up your swords.
Your swords and spears.
Vainamoinen will
lead us to pohjola.
- Yeah.
- And we shall
fight a battle
to release the sun.
Not so, lemminkainen.
Have a seat, lem.
You cannot prevail
with a sword.
Of what use are your swords
against their spells?
I will take
all of you to pohjola.
A class trip?
And each one of you
must hold--
a herring!
- In place of a spear--
- oh.
- Or a blade
- you're making this up,
aren't you?
- A sweetly-sounding--
- it's!
Kantale.
I don't know. Just mad.
And if each of us
carry one of them,
that's a thousand kantales.
- More than that.
- 1,200 at least.
--We have them.
Here in these
ancient pine trees.
We'll cut them down.
Make the harps ourselves.
Great. We spend the winter
making harps.
What're you looking at?
Take all the boats down
to the shores of the frozen sea.
Whatever.
- And you women.
- Back me up on this one.
Take all your jewelry
of silver and gold.
All your earrings.
All your bracelets.
All your naughty things.
--Into the crucible
of illmarinen.
He must have
clear-sounding strings
for our kantales.
Yeah? First he has us
making boats,
then we gotta do the horse.
Now it's the kantales. Ah.
This is the old guy's neck.
This is his head.
And this is his ribcage.
Wow, he's got
the farrah fawcett
exercise stick over there.
Okay, who wants a hot dog?
Still gonna be
a couple of minutes
on the brats.
Just keep this burnt one
for me to nibble on.
Honey, why don't you go get
those marinated steaks ready?
Al, come on.
Don't be too careful.
We just gotta
knock out these kantales.
[Crow groans]
Ow! Carved my own leg
into a kantale.
Hey, uh, anybody care
if I turn on the radio?
Huh. Can you believe it?
Two weeks ago, we were
in shorts out here.
Ladies and gentlemen,
the mormon tabernacle choir
and mountain boys!
Uh, crow,
you are out there, man.
Thank you.
[Joel groans]
But german potato salad
takes a little longer.
It's a boy!
[All quack]
Oh, well, the ice seems safe.
We should've
brought the pickup.
Oh, golly.
[All]
Cigars? Cigarettes?
We come bearing
honey-baked hams.
Tell me,
my fearsome wizards--
okay, you're ugly,
and you smell bad.
What have we here?
Uh, it's an army of warriors
from kalevala.
- Kalelalala?
- And they're all
coming this way.
And there's too many
of them to count!
The year my voice broke!
Come on, we want the sun!
[All]
We want the sun!
Oh.
When kings go senile.
I thought it was
a costume ball!
They're gonna launch him
from a catapult?
[Servo mimics drumroll]
What weapons do they carry?
- Harps.
I wonder, do they think
they're coming
to a wedding feast?
Ha-ha! Good one,
your hideousness.
Liked it. Liked it.
♪♪ [Plays kantale]
L-- ♪ love ♪
♪ soft as an easy chair ♪
Take up your spears!
The ones pointed
with shark's teeth.
Uh, sure, as soon as
this tune is over.
--Steeped in serpent's venom
and kill every one of them!
Uh, did you hear that, sir?
Kill them all!
You know, the music kinda
adds to the drama, actually.
- It does.
- It's all-skate.
Everybody on the ice.
All-skate.
Stalingrad.
The standoff dragged on.
Don't listen to that music!
Wake up! Cover your ears!
Cover them up
with your hands!
That terrible music
will kill us all.
Yeah, well, we put up
with your kenny g,
you... cow.
Welcome to the moody bible
institute prayer hour.
Uh, grandpa,
try another chord.
He's doing
self-indulgent jam.
--Stop them!
Get your swords out!
Use your knife!
Mm, for once,
I'm on her side.
Use your arrows!
Unsheathe your broadswords!
Attack them! Attack them!
Ugh, but I love
prairie home companion.
Any time I can sit and listen,
I love it.
- [Crow snores]
- And that's the news
from lake wobegon,
where the men are strong,
the women are good-looking,
and the children
are above-average.
Oh, butch thompson's gonna
come out with the band.
- [Joel and crow snore]
- Gonna do a medley
of songs about cats.
Then jim ed poole
will do some cat sounds,
and then another episode
of "watching paint dry."
Then claudia schmidt'll
come out
and try to fill
the gap in her teeth.
Ah, then pat donohue
and peter ostroushko
are gonna favor us
with the story
of the swede who
didn't like meatballs.
Then, uh...
Ah, it's so hard to get
good trolls these days.
Oh, it's a mapplethorpe
photo.
Go forth, north wind!
Go forth!
Freeze the people
of kalevala!
Shroud them in
the mantle of death!
[Servo hisses]
Don't look at it, marion!
Don't look!
I said, "harp faster!"
Let's kick into
our grand funk medley!
Um... um, sir,
maybe it's time
to break out the bagpipes.
Ooh!
I say, I hear they
call it mariah.
Well, whatever it is,
it's flippin' freezing!
Yep!
Okay, uh,
do you have a plan b?
All right, new tune.
Everybody.
A one, a two, a one--
oh, forget it.
Heh, it's patton.
You do not belong
in this place of honor!
♪ 'Twas a rock and roll
creation! ♪
Yeah, cream of wheat
stays with you all day,
and that's nice.
Kind of lilting, isn't it?
Go forth, my cloak,
- to the army of kalevala--
- kalevalalala.
- And strangle those warriors
- yep, strangle. Warriors.
Who still remain
on their feet.
And feet. Right. Okay, bye.
Soundtrack by spike jones.
Hey, throw me the cape--
oh. D'oh.
Uh, uh, anybody wanna
throw in here?
This has gotta be
embarrassing.
Yeah, on top of the whole
sampo episode earlier.
Ooh, yeah.
Ugh, cloak
took advantage of me.
We thought the cloak
might try something like this.
- We were prepared.
- Yep.
Look at that.
Oh, it's ruined
'cause it said
"hand wash only"
in cold water.
Stupid cloak.
Stupid, dumb old jerk cloak.
Snot... stupid.
I'm all yours, sir.
Sorry about that.
Now, lemminkainen, you see?
Now you may go in
and set the sun free!
Oh, may I?
- Uh, this thing here?
- Yes!
Glory of kalevala!
I am going to release
the sun from the--
oh, just do it,
and don't screw it up!
Remember the sampo, buddy.
No, what do you want?
Keep away! Keep away!
Oh, the pain! The pain.
Oh, well, that makes it
a lot easier.
Hey, mrs. Witch, can your sun
come out and play?
Ooh.
Hey.
Hey, you know, you don't like
the weather in sweden?
- Just wait a minute, you know?
- [Crow laughs]
Swede blanket bingo!
I'll take sweden, wow!
So they headed for
central minnesota, you know,
to build crystal
and blaine and fridley.
And they made bars
and sought out
church basements
for refuge, and...
Oh, let's see if the torgelsons
want to have a luau tonight.
Yeah, that's a good idea.
Welcome, greg allman!
Hi.
AND WELCOME, ROGER McGUINN!
Howdy.
This is the most emotion
ever expressed in sweden,
- you realize that?
- I did the sun thing, okay?
Thank you, leatherhead.
[Bots chuckle]
May there always be...
It's you!
You brought the birds!
You're evil!
It's the end of the world.
--Always be love
in the world.
Ah... okay.
Lemminkainen and annikki
will be back
in the forests
of secrets and lies.
Neat, huh?
Lemminkainen was
played by john powers.
Not very well, granted.
Annikki by nina anderson.
Donations are being accepted
at the stockholm
spinal research hospital.
Louhi the witch,
by ingrid elhardt.
A woman? Yes, a woman.
Illmarinen
by peter sorenson.
Know these faces,
remember these names.
Vainamoinen by elgin tanner.
James at 92.
If you see
any of these people,
please, for their own sakes,
turn them in.
- Well said.
- ♪ finland finland finland ♪
You know, gypsy,
I just wanted to tell you
how much I enjoyed
your one-woman show earlier.
You know,
it was so confessional.
There were times I actually
felt kind of uncomfortable.
Oh, great, you know,
if you hadn't,
I would've felt I'd failed.
Well, I gotta go
rinse some things.
Okay. See you later.
Hey...
What're you guys doing?
- Guess!
- Um...
- Give up?
- No, you're--
you're the wind
from today's movie.
Nice simplistic
answer, joel.
But we've gone beyond that.
We are delicately
wafting scents
strictly born by the wind
and caressing
your rosy cheek.
Mm, okay.
For example,
I'm a lilac in the spring.
[Servo growls]
- I'm a slice of pie.
- Nice, uh,
creative idea.
- Or I could be a pizza.
- Oh, yeah, with onions
and a kind of low-grade
budget sausage.
Sure, sure. Yeah.
You know, I suppose
I could be the wind,
but I'd be the wind
that comes from your friend
who manages the rialto theater,
if you know what I mean.
And I'm the stench
of bitter failure.
I'm james coco's
oldest pair of boxer shorts.
I'm dick butkus!
Oh, okay. Okay, you two.
I think it's time for us
to read a letter.
Okay? Let's just...
Hey! What was that!
It sounded
like fabric tearing!
- We're going down!
- I'm just-- I'm just--
I'm just-- hey! I'm just--
I'm just opening
the mail bag, okay?
Here's a letter. Uh,
let's put that up
on still store, cambot.
- And there's a picture.
- A picture.
Um, this one comes from
a donna sweeney
- hello, donna!
- And she says,
"I just want to tell you that
my husband brian and I
"are the biggest
mst3000 fans
and have been so
for many years."
- Thank you.
- "Currently my husband and I
reside in germany."
- Ah, germany.
- Um,
"my husband is an army
"bomb disposal expert.
"I am enclosing a photo
"of their
bomb disposal robot
"and I want to let you know
"that he has been
nicknamed crow
- [bots] Huh?
- In honor of crow t. Robot.
- Hey. Let me see that.
- What the--
that is pretty neat.
I think I should show this
to gypsy. She'd probably
- really like it.
- Hey, hey! Help us down!
I'd like to see that!
Joel! Joel!
Can you give us a hand?
We really want
to come down now. D'oh.
Um, joel, i-- you might
want to help us down,
'cause we smell
really good now.
I'm a t.J. Cinnamon bun.
Uh, I'm not interested.
And I'm fresh applesauce--
oh, he's gone.
- Uh, think he'll be back?
- I don't know.
Hey, what's your bag
smell like?
Oh, you don't wanna know.
[Both groan]
Frank, are you
all right up there?
What do you care?
Frank. I care a lot.
Then give me back my money.
And all you care about
is money.
Well, maybe you need
some time alone
to think about
your priorities.
[Frank squeals]
Oh.
♪♪ [Theme]
What's gonna
become of us now?